Guide to the A. E. Coppard Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
A. E. Coppard collection
1919-1951
GEN MSS 815
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.5
(3 boxes)
The A. E. Coppard Collection consists of correspondence and writings by A. E. Coppard which were acquired from various sources. Correspondence primarily contains Coppard's letters to Earl E. Fisk and Thomas Moult; a letter dated Jan. 25, 1923, refers to the death of Katherine Mansfield. Also present are a few letters from Coppard's second wife Winifred, and a letter from Jacob Schwartz to Earl E. Fisk, enclosing a letter from Coppard to Schwartz. Writings contains drafts of several short stories, some with printer's proofs.
Coppard, A. E. (Alfred Edgar), 1878-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials acquired from various sources, as noted in the contents list.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1919-1951. II. Writings, 1935-1948.
A. E. Coppard (1878–1957)
Alfred Edgar Coppard was a British short-story writer and poet.
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of correspondence and writings by A. E. Coppard. There are 47 letters from Coppard to Earl E. Fisk, accompanied by 3 letters from Coppard's second wife, Winifred May Coppard, Christmas cards, clippings from book catalogues, and publishers' advertisements. A snapshot of Coppard accompanies a letter of August 19, 1931. There are seven letters to Thomas Moult; a letter dated January 25, 1923 refers to the death of Katherine Mansfield. A letter from Jacob Schwartz to Earl E. Fisk has as an enclosure a letter from Coppard to Schwartz. Also present is a folder of publishers' rejection slips for stories submitted to various American magazines.
The writings consist of drafts of his short stories "Ahoy! Sailor Boy," "The Ballet Girl," "Count Stefan," "Dark Knowledge," "The Fair Young Willowy Tree," "Fifty Pounds," "The Gollan," "The Higgler," "Luxury," "Ninepenny Flute," "Nixey's Harlequin," "Polly Morgan," "Ring the Bells of Heaven," "Simple Simon," "The Smith of Pretty Peter," "Three-Handed Reel," and "The Tiger." The Collected Tales of A. E. Coppard is boxed separately, and contains the printer's copy and proofs, with corrections by the author.
Authors, British -- 20th Century -- Archives; British literature -- 20th Century; Coppard, A. E. (Alfred Edgar), 1878-1957; Coppard, Winifred; Fisk, Earl E.; Mansfield, Katherine, 1888-1923; Moult, Thomas; Schwartz, Jacob, 1899-
- Correspondence, 1919-1951; Series I
  - A. E. Coppard to Earl E. Fisk, 1929-1951 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    43 ALS, 1 TL, and 3 TLS; enclosure: copy of TLS to Alfred A. Knopf, August 7, 1946, and reply. Accompanied by 3 ALS, Winifred Coppard to Earl E. Fisk, 1946-1950, 9 p; two Christmas cards; clippings from book catalogues, and publishers' advertisements. Snapshot of Coppard with letter of August 19, 1931.
  - A. E. Coppard to Thomas Moult, Headington and Henley-on-Thames, 1919-1926 (Box 1)
    7 ALS; in the letter of January 25, 1923, Coppard speaks of the death of Katherine Mansfield.
  - Jacob Schwartz to Earl E. Fisk, London, 1930 (Box 1)
    1 ALS; enclosure: ALS from A. E. Coppard to Jacob Schwartz, June 30, 1930.
  - Publisher's rejection slips for stories submitted to various American magazines by Earl E. Fisk, 1931 Jan-Sep (Box 3)
- Writings, 1935-1948; Series II
  - The Collected Tales of A. E. Coppard, printer's copy and proofs, with corrections by the author, [n.p.], 1947-1948 (Box 2)
    The printer's copy consists of printed pages cut from books, old galley proofs and typescripts (673 p. in all); this is accompanied by galley proofs (180 p.) and plate proofs (514 p.). Published: New York, Knopf, 1948.
  - "Ahoy! Sailor Boy," corrected typescript of the short story, and 2 later typescripts, Abingdon, undated (Box 3)
    Published in Dunky Fitlow, London, Jonathan Cape, 1933.
  - "Count Stefan," autograph manuscript, 3 notebooks, undated (Box 3)
    Published by The Golden Cockerel Press, 1928. In blue cloth case.
  - "Dark Knowledge," 2 typescripts and 1 carbon, Abingdon, undated (Box 3)
    Published in Nixey's Harlequin, London, Jonathan Cape, 1931
  - "The Fair Young Willowy Tree," autograph manuscript of the short story, [n.p.], 1938 (Box 3)
    Published in You Never Know, Do You? and Other Tales, London, Methuen, 1939.
  - "Fifty Pounds," autograph manuscript, final draft from which the typescript was made, undated (Box 3)
    General note
    Gift of John Hay Whitney
  - "The Gollan," corrected carbon typescript, Abingdon, undated (Box 3)
    Published in Nixey's Harlequin, London, Jonathan Cape, 1931.
  - "The Higgler," autograph manuscript in pencil, undated (Box 3)
    Page 3 only. Written on back of typescript of p.18 of another manuscript. Removed from his The Higgler, New York, 1930 (no. 3 of an edition of 39 copies).
  - "Luxury," typescript of the short story, Oxford, undated (Box 3)
    Published in The Black Dog and Other Stories, London, Jonathan Cape, 1923.
  - "Ninepenny Flute," autograph manuscript of the short story, 1935 Mar 14 (Box 3)
    Published: Ninepenny Flute, London, Macmillan, 1937.
  - "Nixey's Harlequin," typescript of the short story, Abingdon, undated (Box 3)
    Published: Nixey's Harlequin, London, Jonathan Cape, 1931.
  - "Polly Morgan," carbon typescript of the short story, used as printer's copy, Abingdon, undated (Box 3)
    Published in Silver Circus, London, Jonathan Cape, [1928].
  - "Ring the Bells of Heaven," autograph manuscript, corrected, with ALS to an unnamed correspondent concerning the manuscript, Walberswich, Southwold, 1937 Mar 15 (Box 3)
    Gift of Philip M. Neufeld in honor of Maurice M. Rosen
  - "The Smith of Pretty Peter," 2 typescripts, Abingdon, undated (Box 3)
  - "Three-Handed Reel," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 3)
    Published in Fishmonger's Fiddle, [1925]. Written on versos of typed copies of "The Ballet Girl" (complete), "Simple Simon" (complete), and "The Tiger" (1 leaf only). All published in The Black Dog, London [1923]. In maroon cloth case; gift of Ray L. Murphy.